Leon Howard Sullivan Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Leon Howard Sullivan Papers 1940-2002 1988-2002
MSS85101
Sullivan, Leon Howard, 1922-2001
8,400 items
24 containers
9.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Civil rights leader, entrepreneur, and minister. Correspondence, speeches, subject files, clippings, printed material, awards, and other papers relating chiefly to Sullivan’s work with the International Foundation for Education and Self Help.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Sullivan, Leon Howard, 1922-2001.
Organizations
African-African American Summit.; General Motors Corporation.; International Foundation for Education and Self Help.; OIC International.; Opportunities Industrialization Centers of America.
Subjects
African Americans--Economic conditions.; African Americans--Relations with Africans.; African Americans--Social conditions.; Community development--Africa.; Economic assistance, American--Africa--Congresses.; Economic assistance, American--Africa.; Economic assistance, Domestic--United States.; Economic development--Africa.; Medical assistance--Africa.; Medical care--Africa.; Poverty--Africa.; Social responsibility of business.; Technical assistance, American--Africa--Congresses.; Technical assistance, American--Africa.; Unemployment--Africa.
Places
Africa--Economic conditions--1960-; Africa--Relations--United States.; Africa--Social conditions--1960-; South Africa.; United States--Economic conditions--1945-; United States--Relations--Africa.; United States--Social conditions--1945-
Occupations
Civil rights leaders.; Clergy.; Entrepreneurs.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Leon Howard Sullivan were given to the Library of Congress in 2004 and 2007 by Leon Sullivan’s wife, Grace Banks Sullivan.
Transfers
One VHS tape containing documentaries of notable West Virginians was transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where it is identified as part of these papers.
Other Repositories
Other papers of Leon Howard Sullivan are held by the Stuart A. Rose Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library at Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Leon Howard Sullivan are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1922, Oct. 6 Born, Charleston, W.V.
1943 B.A., West Virginia State College, Institute, W.V.
1945 Married Grace Banks (died 2011)
1945 Pastor, First Baptist Church, South Orange, N.J.
1947 M.A., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1950 Pastor, Zion Baptist Church, Philadelphia, Pa.
1962 Founder, Zion Non-Profit Charitable Trust, Philadelphia, Pa.
1964 Founder, Opportunities Industrialization Centers of America, Philadelphia, Pa.
1969 Founder, OIC International, Philadelphia, Pa.
1971 Board member, General Motors Corp.
1977 Created Sullivan Principles promoting corporate social responsibility
1988 Retired, Zion Baptist Church, Philadelphia, Pa.
1988 Founder, International Foundation for Education and Self Help, Phoenix, Ariz.
1991 Awarded Presidential Medal of Freedom
1998 Published Moving Mountains: The Principles and Purposes of Leon Sullivan. Valley Forge, Pa.: Judson Press
1999 Received Eleanor Roosevelt Award for Human Rights
2001, Apr. 24 Died, Scottsdale, Ariz.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Leon Howard Sullivan (1922-2001) span the years 1940-2002 with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1988-2002. The collection consists primarily of correspondence, reports, personal files, program files, articles, and miscellaneous material from Sullivan’s role as president of the International Foundation for Education and Self Help (IFESH), with additional material regarding Opportunities Industrialization Centers of America. The papers are arranged in three series: IFESH, OIC, and Personal Miscellany.
Leon Sullivan devoted many years of his life to the Philadelphia community, serving as pastor of the Zion Baptist Church from 1950 until his retirement in 1988. In that span, Sullivan founded the Zion Non-Profit Charitable Trust in 1962, Opportunities Industrialization Centers of America in 1964, the OIC International in 1969, and served on the board of directors for General Motors beginning in the 1970s, where he developed a code of conduct for companies called the Sullivan Principles.
After his retirement, Sullivan founded the International Foundation for Education and Self Help, which would extend his principles of self-help and community empowerment to Africa. Through the use of assistance programs, IFESH helped educate and train Africans in the areas of health, business, and economic development in order to reduce poverty and unemployment. As president, Sullivan began the African-African American Summit to bring together world leaders and highlight issues facing African countries. The IFESH series contains program files, reports, summit materials, contributions, and administrative files documenting the various functions of the organization.
While serving as president of IFESH, Sullivan was kept abreast of the operations of Opportunities Industrialization Centers of America. The OIC series contains information regarding OIC International, affiliates, reports, and miscellaneous administrative records. The Personal Miscellany series contains correspondence, press and news clippings, articles written by Sullivan, and assorted material concerning General Motors, South Africa, and the Sullivan Principles.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
International Foundation for Education and Self Help, 1982-2002
Opportunities Industrialization Centers, 1976-2001
Personal Miscellany, 1940-2001
Container List
- International Foundation for Education and Self Help, 1982-2002 (Box 1-12)
  Program files, reports, adminstrative files, subject files, and news articles relating to the International Foundation for Education and Self Help.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Administrative file (Box 1)
    - Board meetings, 1991-1993
    - Budgets and financial statements, 1992-1999, (2 folders)
    - Incorporation, 1983-1987
    - Insurance, 1995
  - African-African American Summit
    - 1st Summit, Abidjan, Côte d'Ivoire, 1991
    - 2nd Summit, Libreville, Gabon, 1993, (2 folders)
    - 3rd Summit, Dakar, Senegal, 1995, (2 folders)
    - 4th Summit, Harare, Zimbabwe, 1997, (5 folders) (Box 2)
    - 5th Summit, Accra, Ghana, 1999
    - 6th Summit, Abuja, Nigeria, 2001
    - Summit dinner, 2000, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Contributions, 1988-2000, (5 folders)
  - Newsletters, 1990-2002 (Box 4)
  - Press, 1991-2001, (3 folders)
  - Printed matter, 1983-1996, (2 folders)
  - Program files
    - Angola projects, 1994-1996, (1 folder)
    - Angola projects, 1994-1996, (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - Debt for Development, 1988-1996, (2 folders)
    - International Fellows Program, 1991-1998, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Miscellany, 1989-2000
    - People's Investment Fund for Africa, 1999-2001, (2 folders)
    - People's Investment Fund for Africa, 1999-2001, (1 folder) (Box 7)
    - Program updates and overviews, 1991-1995, (2 folders)
    - Proposals, 1991-2000, (3 folders)
    - Proposals, 1991-2000, (1 folder) (Box 8)
    - Schools for Africa, 1997-2000
    - Self Help Investment Plan, 1994-1998, (4 folders)
    - Self Help Investment Plan, 1994-1998, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Supporters of Sub-Saharan Africa, 1994-2001, (4 folders)
    - Teachers for Africa, 1992-2001, (1 folder)
    - Teachers for Africa, 1992-2001, (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - Reports, 1988-1999, (2 folders)
  - Reports, 1988-1999, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Subject files
    - Congress, 1990-2000
    - HIV/AIDS, 2000, (2 folders)
    - Literacy, 1982-1993
    - Miscellany, 1992-2000, (2 folders)
    - National Student's Support Council for Africa, 1993 (Box 12)
    - Peru, 1990
    - Receptions, 1991-2000
    - Southern African Enterprise Development Fund, 1995-2000, (3 folders)
    - Unesco, 1996
    - World Bank, 1992-2000
- Opportunities Industrialization Centers, 1976-2001 (Box 12-16)
  Program files, reports, administrative files, subject files, and news articles relating to Opportunities Industrialization Centers of America and OIC International.
  - Affiliates
    - American Indian, 1994-2000
    - General file, 1991-2000 (Box 13)
    - Greater Saginaw, Mich., 1996-1998
    - Los Angeles, Calif., 1993-1998
    - Miscellaneous affiliates, 1994-2000
    - Philadelphia, Pa., 1993-1997
    - Yakima Valley, Wash., 1996-1998
  - Articles, 1986, 1996
  - Conferences, 1990-2001
  - Correspondence, 1976, 1989-2000
  - Essence of OIC, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Executive board, 1989-2001
  - Finances, 1995-2001
  - International, 1980-2000, (5 folders)
  - International, 1980-2000, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Miscellany, 1990-1998
  - Press, 1988-2000
  - Reports
    - Annual reports, 1980-1995
    - Miscellany, 1989-1995, (2 folders)
    - Proposals, 1989-1998, (2 folders) (Box 16)
- Personal Miscellany, 1940-2001 (Box 16-24)
  Correspondence, speeches, news articles, awards, reports, and writings related to Sullivan's work outside of International Foundation for Education and Self and Opportunities Industrialization Centers.
  - Articles, 1968-1996
  - Assault on Literacy Program, 1989
  - Awards and tributes
    - Miscellany, 1988-2000, (2 folders)
    - Presidential Medal of Freedom, 1991
    - Tribute to Greatness: The Sullivan Years, 1992
  - Biographical information, 1988 (Box 17)
  - Book file, 1972, 1996-2000, (5 folders)
  - Correspondence
    - 1988, (1 folder)
    - 1988, (1 folder) (Box 18)
    - 1989, (3 folders)
    - 1990
    - 1991
    - 1992
    - 1993, (2 folders)
    - 1994 (Box 19)
    - 1995
    - 1996
    - 1997, (2 folders)
    - 1998
    - 1999
    - 2000, (2 folders)
    - 2000, (1 folder) (Box 20)
    - 2001
    - Undated
  - Documentary, 1994
  - Finances, 1972-1996, (2 folders)
  - Funeral services, 1994-2000
  - General Motors, 1971-2000, (2 folders)
  - General Motors, 1971-2000, (5 folders) (Box 21)
  - Notes, undated, (1 folder)
  - Notes, undated, (1 folder) (Box 22)
  - Photograhs, circa 1975-circa 1995
  - Poems, 1940, 1989
  - Press, 1990-2001, (2 folders)
  - Progress Investment Associates, 1997-2000
  - Remembrances and condolences, 2001, (2 folders)
  - Solicitations, 1989-2001, (1 folder)
  - Solicitations, 1989-2001, (3 folders) (Box 23)
  - South Africa, 1978-1996, (4 folders)
  - Speeches, 1978-2000, (2 folders) (Box 24)
  - Sullivan Principles, circa 1977-2001, (2 folders)
  - Temple University, Philadelphia, Pa., 1989
  - Zion Baptist Church, Philadelphia, Pa., 1980-1997
  - Zion Community Center, Philadelphia, Pa., 1990-1996
  - Zion Non-Profit Charitable Trust, 1996